On May 29th, 1453,
Constantinople fell. Constantine XI,
last emperor of the Romans, fell in the
battle as the Ottoman armies under
Mehmed II broke through the walls and
slew the last defenders of one of
Christianity's oldest and proudest
cities. The loss of Constantinople to
Muslim conquerors was a tragedy for
Christians, one that still stings many
to this day. However, when the Ottoman
armies were knocking at the city's gate,
the rest of Christendom [music] was
nowhere to be found. Despite knowing an
attack was coming, the Christian
kingdoms of Europe sent almost nothing
to help their Eastern brethren against
their common foe. So, why didn't Europe
try to defend Constantinople when it
needed it most?
Context and Crusades. The question is
not a random one. Europe had been
sending Christian armies to fight
Muslims in the East for 400 years before
Constantinople fell. The First Crusade
had been called by Pope Urban II in 1095
at the request of the Byzantine Emperor
Alexios I Komnenos as a [music] response
to the invading armies of the Seljuk
Turks. Both East and West [music] had
proven they were willing to set aside
minor differences and unite as
Christians against Muslim Turk [music]
invaders. Therefore, it is fair to ask
why Europe did [music] not rally in 1453
to aid the descendants of Alexios
against attack by the descendants of
those same Seljuk Turks. In reality,
much had changed since the First
Crusade. Relations between East and West
had not improved [music]
with time. By 1095, the Great Schism was
still fresh, and there was genuine hope
that it might be repaired soon. 400
years later, the idea of reunifying
Christendom had been dismissed as a
fantasy by [music] many. Also, while the
Crusaders may have started as a way to
aid Constantinople, they quickly became
its worst nightmare. In 1203, French and
Venetians on the Fourth Crusade had
stopped by Constantinople on route to
Jerusalem and overthrew the existing
Byzantine emperor in favor of another
candidate who promised to support them.
However, a few months later, with that
support nowhere to be seen, the
Crusaders overthrew that emperor, too,
and installed a Latin Christian
government in Constantinople instead. It
took 60 years for the Byzantines to
retake the city, but Constantinople and
its relations with the West never truly
recovered. This long, fractured
relationship meant that by the 1450s, it
was not so simple for Europe to rush to
the city's aid. Ottoman might. There was
also the fact that the Ottomans were an
intimidating threat. By 1450, the
Ottomans had all but destroyed the
Byzantine Empire. The once-proud state
was reduced to the city of
Constantinople, and most of its former
territory [music]
had already been captured.
This included European territory in
Greece and the Balkans, which cut off a
major land route that Europe may have
used to come to their aid.
The truth was that there wasn't a
Byzantine Empire left to save, and
everyone expected the lone city of
Constantinople [music] to fall
eventually. The Ottoman armies were
fearsome, and they had already proven
themselves in battle against the
Europeans many times. In 1396, a
coalition of French, Italian, Hungarian,
and other Europeans attacked the city of
Nicopolis in Bulgaria, which had
recently been captured by the Ottomans
in what became known as the Nicopolis
Crusade. The Ottoman armies crushed the
Crusaders, wiping out most of the army
and effectively ending Western European
crusading for good.
More recently in 1444,
Hungary and Poland launched the last
true crusade to kick the Ottomans out of
the Balkans. That, too, was a disaster.
Most of the 50,000 man army was wiped
out at the Battle of Varna, and the
Polish King Vladislav was lost in
battle. The defeats of the Varna Crusade
was the end of serious crusading efforts
from Europe, and the memory of its
failure was fresh in European minds when
news of Constantinople's situation
arrived.
All of these factors made it difficult
for any European country to consider
helping Constantinople in its hour of
need.
Europe in chaos.
There was also the fact that Europe had
its own internal problems to deal with.
The Holy Roman Emperor Frederick III had
only been crowned in 1452 and was far
too busy securing his own power to worry
about Constantinople.
The political uncertainty of his new
reign also meant that the countless
smaller nobles under him were more
worried about protecting their lands
from rivals than in raising armies to
fight foreign wars. France had problems
of its own, too. After over a century of
warfare, it was finally reaching the end
of its Hundred Years War with England.
The French had recaptured Normandy in
1450 and were busy campaigning against
England's last major continental holding
in Gascony by the time messengers
arrived with the news of
Constantinople's danger.
France, not to mention their English
opponents, were in no position to call
off their own war to go fight another
one far away. Meanwhile, the kingdoms of
Castile and Portugal had their own wars
against Muslims to deal with. The
Reconquista was in full swing and there
was little reason to rush to the other
side of the continent to fight Turks
when there were still Muslim cities and
fortresses at home to be conquered. Nor
could the great European powers like
Hungary or Poland do much to help. Both
were still recovering from the losses at
Varna a few years earlier.
Furthermore, with no navies to speak of
and the Ottomans in control of Greece
and the Balkans, Hungarian and Polish
support couldn't have reached
Constantinople even if they wanted to.
It seemed all of Europe was too
distracted to help.
Constantine's only hope was to appeal to
Italy and to the Pope himself.
The Pope.
In summer 1451,
Constantine dispatched an ambassador,
Andronicus Sphrantzes Leontaris, to
Italy in a final desperate attempt to
get support.
But the odds were already stacked
against him.
No one felt the schism [music] between
East and West more strongly than the
Pope.
Constantine knew that getting any real
help would require extraordinary efforts
to mend that relationship. Efforts
Constantine was surprisingly willing
[music] to make.
When his ambassador arrived in Rome, he
presented Pope Nicholas V with an offer
of joining a church council in
Constantinople [music]
to discuss the possibility of church
reunification.
It was an exceptional offer and one that
the Orthodox clergy, including the
Patriarch of Constantinople himself,
strongly opposed. However, the Pope
declined the offer of a council in
Constantinople and reiterated his hope
that the East would accept papal
supremacy anyway.
Still, the Pope understood the danger of
allowing such an important Christian
city to fall into Muslim hands without
doing something.
So, in May 1452, he appointed Isidore of
Kiev as papal legate of Constantinople
with instructions to bring some troops
to the city as a token of Western
support. Isidore arrived in
Constantinople a few months later with
200 Neapolitan archers.
This small force could never hope to
turn the tide of the battle to come, but
their arrival was encouraging for the
increasingly [music] desperate people of
the city. It was a statement that the
Western Christians would send aid, but
only if they accepted the Pope's terms.
There were many in the city who thought
this was a fair trade, including
apparently the emperor. Constantine
signaled his support for union with the
West and invited Isidore to ceremonies
in the Hagia Sophia, where they
proclaimed the reunion of the Eastern
and Western churches.
While this move earned some approval
from the city's populace, it was opposed
by many of the clergy who saw it as a
cheap betrayal of the faith done for
purely practical reasons. Modern
scholars believe the emperor was simply
doing what he could to gain support for
the immediate crisis. And there is
nothing to suggest Constantine had any
intention of reuniting the churches in
the long run. Either way, it did not
convince the Pope or anyone else to send
additional support. Italian cities,
Constantinople's final hope lay with the
city-states of Italy. Cities like Venice
and Genoa had long-established alliances
with Constantinople. Italian ships were
a common sight in the city's ports, and
there was a sizeable community of
Italian merchants in the city. If anyone
in Europe had a reason to care about
what happened to Constantinople, it was
them. The trouble was that these same
cities were also friendly with the
Ottomans. The Ottomans were already the
dominant power in the Eastern
Mediterranean and were much more
important trading partners than
Constantinople could ever be. [music]
The Italian cities had a lot to lose by
angering the Sultan, and they had no
reason to think that an
Ottoman-controlled Constantinople
wouldn't welcome their ships just as
happily as they did in every other
Ottoman port. The Italian cities,
therefore, found themselves in a tough
situation. On one side, their old but
weak Christian ally. On the other, their
stronger and wealthier Muslim friends.
But, that was ignoring the fact that
Italy, like elsewhere in Europe, had its
own problems. The Italian cities were in
a state of near constant war or
preparation for war with each other, and
things were no different in the early
1450s. Most Italian cities were occupied
with the chaotic war of Milanese
succession at the time, which meant they
had almost nothing to spare for
Constantinople. In the end, the Italians
could do little more than the rest of
Europe. The Venetian Senate voted 74 to
7 to support Constantinople, but that
support was purely vocal, and not a
single ship or soldier was officially
sent. Other cities, like Genoa and
Ragusa, expressed similar [music] vocal
support for their Christian cousins, but
words were all they had. In the end,
none of the Italian cities sent official
support to Constantinople. Unofficially,
though, there were a handful of
Europeans who did answer the call. Who
did Europe send? First and foremost of
these was the Genoese mercenary Giovanni
Giustiniani. Giustiniani had years of
experience fighting in Italy and had a
particular talent for siege defense.
Upon learning of the threats to
Constantinople, Giustiniani set sail
with 400 Genoese mercenaries boosted by
a further 300 men from the Genoese
controlled island of Chios to defend the
city. The emperor recognized
Giustiniani's military experience as
invaluable and assigned him to lead the
defense of the walls around the gate of
Saint Romanos. Giustiniani and the
Genoese fought admirably in the battle
and held off several serious attacks on
the walls that may have taken the city
if they had not prevented it. However,
on the morning of May 29th, Giustiniani
was fatally wounded by an Ottoman
cannon. His downfall shattered the
already fragile morale of the defenders
and the city fell within hours. There
were also other Europeans already in the
city who joined the defense. Historical
sources describe Venetian, Genoese, and
other Italian residents in the city
joining the defense against the
Ottomans. There were also numerous
individuals from all over Europe and
beyond who found themselves in the city
when the Ottomans arrived and stepped up
to help the defense. Perhaps known of
these was Johannes Grant, a German or
possibly Scottish military engineer who
organized the use of fire to stop the
Ottomans building tunnels to undermine
the city walls. Conclusion. Of course,
the Ottomans would triumph [music] in
the end. It is impossible to know how
much more support would have been needed
to successfully defend the city.
However, in the long run, it probably
wouldn't have mattered. The Ottomans
were so strong by that point that had
they lost in 1453, they surely would
have returned a few years later for
another try. The truth was that
Constantinople was on [music] borrowed
time for years before it finally fell.
Even if Europe had sent help to save it
in 1453, they would have only bought the
isolated city a bit [music] more time
before the Ottomans returned with all
their might once more.
If you'd like to help us keep creating
and get early access to our videos,
[music]
behind-the-scenes content, and other
perks, consider becoming a member right
here on YouTube or joining us on
Patreon. Every bit of support helps. And
as always, thank you so much for
watching.